Guide to the Kenaga Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Kenaga family papers
1851-1908
WA MSS S-1310
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.75
(5 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence and printed material documenting the lives of several Kenagas, Baers, and Reists of New York, California, and several midwest states.
Kanagy family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Kenaga Family Papers were purchased in 1963 from Edward Eberstadt and Company with income from the Coe. No. 1 Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
FAMILY CHARTS
Family charts for the Baer, Kenaga, and Reist families are found on the next four pages. They are designed to show the kinship ties of the major correspondents and of persons prominently referred to in the letters. They are based on the best evidence available, but are by no means complete.
Benjamin, David, Joseph, and Levi Baer called Benjamin Kenaga "cousin." It is not known who the common ancestor was, but it was probably in the generation of Benjamin's grandparents. The Kenaga and Reist families are connected by the 1854 marriage of Benjamin Kenaga and Fanny Reist. BAER FAMILY
David Baer (-1898) m. Mary (1833-1901)
Joseph Baer (1832-1905)
Levi W. Baer (1839-1905)
Benjamin F. Baer (1842-) m. 1876 Margaret (1855-
Elizabeth Baer
Note: The names of important correspondents are underlined. KENAGA FAMILY-1
Benjamin Kenaga (1808-1903) m. Ester (-1892) * Benjamin Kenaga (-1907) m. 1854 Fanny Reist (-1897)
Joseph Kenaga m. 1871 Sarah
Sarah Kenaga m. 1864 Jefferson Fogelsonger
Levi Kenaga (-1891)
John Kenaga
Anna Kenaga (-1901) m. 1858 John Fogelsonger
Jacob Kenaga m. Fanny Gray
Note: * Please refer to another chart for additional information. KENAGA FAMILY-2
Benjamin Kenaga ( -1907) m. 1854 Fanny Reist (-1897)
Joanna Kenaga m. Dewitt Casler
Susan Kenaga m. Nelson A. Lockwood
Lillian Kenaga (1860-) m. 1882 Charles L. Wickens
Ira Eugene Kenaga (1863-) m. 1889
Una Kenaga (1866-) m. William Chaffee
Otto L. Kenaga (1868-
Allen Elmer Kenaga REIST FAMILY
John Reist (-1879) m. Anna (-1885)
Elizabeth Reist (1822-) m. Abraham Barton * Fanny Reist (-1897) m. 1854 Benjamin Kenaga (-1907)
Jacob Reist m. Maria
Susan Reist (1833-) m. 1854 Christian S. Frick
Daniel Reist m. Sabina
Elias Reist m. Flora [Long?]
Christian Reist (-1870)
John Reist m. 1851 Nancy Long
Scope and Contents
The Kenaga Family Papers consist primarily of letters sent to Benjamin Kenaga and his wife Fanny Reist Kenaga from relatives and friends, plus a small quantity of printed material. The papers span the dates 1851-1908.
Series I, Correspondence, holds four boxes of correspondence, alphabetically arranged by author. Most of the letters were written to Benjamin and Fanny Reist Kenaga by Baer, Fogelsonger, Frick, Kenaga, Lockwood, Long, Miller, and Reist relatives. Five folders (Box 2, folders 48-52) contain letters between Fanny Reist Kenaga and her husband. Most were written between August 11 and November 21, 1864, when Benjamin Kenaga was on active duty with the 98th Regiment of the National Guard of the State of New York.
The correspondence consists almost entirely of personal letters devoted to news of family and friends and of farm life. The birth of children, illness and death of relatives and acquaintances, crop prices, economic conditions, weather, religion, and careers are frequent topics of discussion. In addition, the letters of several correspondents discuss the Civil War, politics in the last third of the nineteenth century, and gold mining in the West.
Benjamin and Fanny Kenaga spent much of their lives in Disco and Clyde, Michigan, but their relatives settled throughout the northern and western United States. The correspondence of Christian Frick, Eli Long, and members of the Kenaga and Reist families tell much about Williamsville, New York, where Benjamin and Fanny lived until 1866. Christian and William Miller wrote about Monticello, Indiana. John Zimmerman lived in Gilbertsville, Indiana, and Levi Kenaga and Christian Reist worked in the gold fields in Tuolumne County, California.
Since most of the correspondents were related by birth or marriage, the letters are full of news about the lives of mutual acquaintances. The correspondence of Benjamin F. Baer, David Baer, Joanna Kenaga Casler, Jefferson Fogelsonger, Susan Reist Frick, Fanny Kenaga, Maria Miller Lockwood, Eli Long, Elias Reist, and Lillian Snyder, for example, report births, marriages, illnesses, and deaths of three generations of friends and relatives. In a March 6, 1874 letter, cousin Benjamin F. Baer of Monticello, Indiana, tells Benjamin Kenaga that he was the father of a seven month old boy, that brother Levi Baer is well, and that sister Betsy married "a worthless fellow." Several 1896-99 letters discuss the heart condition and death of brother David Baer. Elias Reist, who spent his entire life in Erie County, New York, provided a running commentary on the health of the Reists; Christian Miller wrote about the life of the the Seneca County, Ohio, cousins; and Charles and Lillian Kenaga Wickens told of their children, discussed a series of clerkships Charles held, and worried about the declining health of Fanny Kenaga.
Religion was frequently discussed by such correspondents as Benjamin F. Baer, Elizabeth Reist Barton, Eliza Segar Cook, Ira E. Kenaga, Elias Reist, John Zimmerman, and most importantly by Fanny's father, John Reist. He was a lay minister who preached regularly throughout western New York State and Canada. In addition to discussing baptisms and his preaching tours, which he characterized as "appointments for communion," he continually urged his daughter and son-in-law to seek salvation. The letters of Elias Reist increasingly took on a religious tone after he announced on November 27, 1890, that he and his wife "have come out publicly for our saviour Jesus Christ." A similar trend occurred in the letters of John Zimmerman of Gilbertsville, Iowa, after he was baptized in the summer of 1890.
The important correspondents were neither well educated nor prosperous. Most were farmers, but some were clerks, millers, and miners. Benjamin and David Baer provided information on farm life in Monticello, Indiana; Christian and William Miller farmed in Seneca County, Ohio; and John Zimmerman was a farmer in Gilbertsville, Black Hawk County, Iowa. Elias Reist was a miller in Erie County, New York, and Benjamin's son, Ira E. Kenaga, worked for the Reist Milling Company 1885-88. Charles L. Wickens clerked for several Michigan and Wisconsin railroad companies.
Levi Kenaga and brother-in-law Christian Reist were miners. Levi sailed for California in 1859 and spent most of the next dozen years prospecting in the gold fields of the mother lode country around Jamestown, Tuolumne County, California. From October 1872 until July 1876 Levi Kenaga lived in Columbus, Nevada. He moved to the Black Hills of South Dakota in 1876, but had returned to California by 1878. In 1883 he was in Seattle still looking for mining work. Levi Kenaga was unsuccessful in his search for riches in the gold fields, although his letters suggest that Christian Reist was considerably more prosperous. Despite being severely bitten by the gold bug, Levi probably realized that he had little chance to strike it rich and thus urged brother Benjamin not to come to California. In his letters he also wrote about the lawlessness in the California mining camps, talked about his 1876 involvement in Nevada to a woman whose husband was supposed to be dead, and in 1876-77 discussed the Indian problem in the Black Hills.
The Civil War is discussed in the letters of Levi W. Baer, Elias Fogelsonger, Benjamin and Fanny Kenaga, Levi Kenaga, Christian F. Miller, and John Zimmerman. Levi Baer served in the 46th Regiment of the Indiana Volunteers, and three 1863 letters describe the Vicksburg campaign. He also complained about soldiering, railed against officers, and asserted in a November 1862 letter that he "did not enlist to fight for to free these damed slaves." Elias Fogelsonger was a cavalryman in the 10th Regiment of the New York Volunteers, Porter Guards, in the Army of the Potomac. In an August 1863 letter he described what the battlefield at Bull Run looked like. "Arms, legs, jaws, skulls, and all shapes of human bones and flesh can be seen." He alternated between enjoyment of military life and disgust.
Benjamin Kenaga, an anti-war Democrat, was called to active duty in August 1864 for one hundred days and spent most of his term of service guarding rebel prisoners at Elmira. His wife Fanny wrote to him of her anxiety and her fear that he might be called to the front, while Benjamin's letters to Fanny describe guard duty and the upcoming presidential election. Since he favored McClellan, he was not released from active duty until the election was over. The most interesting Civil War letters, however, are those of Christian F. Miller, a staunch Unionist. Miller, who hired a substitute after being drafted, engaged in a long dialogue with Kenaga in which he professed his devotion to the Union and attacked his cousin for his support of Clement Vallandigham and the peace movement. Benjamin Kenaga's military career was brief and inglorious, but as memories dimmed he attended GAR encampments and from 1887-89 sought a pension as compensation for an attack of sunstroke suffered on the parade ground (See Box 5, folder 140).
A number of correspondents commented on national politics, including Benjamin F. Baer, Elias Fogelsonger, John Kenaga, Levi Kenaga, Lucius J. Kenaga, Maria Miller Lockwood, Christian F. Miller, and John Zimmerman. Most of Benjamin Kenaga's correspondents were Republicans, whose sentiments were expressed by Christian Miller in a May 10, 1868 letter: "As to Andrew Johnson... It would be an injustice to Benedict Arnold to place him in the same light with the above said trator." Benjamin Baer, however, also mentioned the Grangers in November 1874 and the Farmer's Alliance in 1890, Lucius J. Kenaga endorsed the aims of the Knights of Labor in 1886, and John Zimmerman mixed religion and the protective tariff in an 1892 letter.
Other subjects are discussed in the correspondence. Cousin Lucius J. Kenaga, for example, mentioned electric lights in Terre Haute, Indiana in February 1886; son Ira E. Kenaga noted in 1888 that he was vice president of the Williamsville, New York Prohibition Club; brother Levi in several early letters discussed California fruits; and Christian Miller wrote about using the telephone.
Series II, Other Papers, includes advertisements, insurance papers, pension papers, photographs, regimental orders, subscription information, and lists. Two folders contain advertisements for coffee, patent medicine, school supplies, soap, watches, and the like. Floraplexion and Warner's Safe Cure, patent medicines that supposedly cured most known diseases, were probably purchased for Fanny Kenaga, who was ailing and crippled for the last decade of her life. The pension papers consist primarily of letters from former soldiers in the 98th Regiment of the New York National Guard who had been asked to recall Kenaga's attack of sunstroke. The collection contains two photographs; and undated tintype and an 1864 carte de visite of Fanny Kenaga holding an infant. Benjamin Kenaga had a longstanding subscription to The Amherst Bee, published in Williamsville, and also received The Buffalo Courier. The collection concludes with three folders of lists of letters in the Kenaga Family Papers.
Death; Families; Farm life; Gold mines and mining -- California; Lay ministry -- New York (State); Lay preaching; Old age; California -- Economic conditions; Erie County (N.Y.); Gilbertsville (Iowa); Indiana -- Economic conditions; Iowa -- Economic conditions; Jamestown (Calif.); Monticello (Ind.); New York (State) -- Social life and customs; Ohio -- Economic conditions; Seneca County (Ohio); Tuolumne County (Calif.); United States -- History -- 1865-1898; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Farmers -- United States; Millers -- United States; Miners -- United States; Baer, Benjamin F., 1842-; Baer, Joseph, 1832-1905; Baer, Levi W., 1839-1905; Fogelsonger, Elias; Frick, Susan Reist, 1833-; Kenaga, Benjamin, d.1907; Kenaga, Fanny Reist, d. 1897; Kenaga, Ira Eugene, 1863-; Kenaga, Joseph; Kenaga, Levi, d. 1891; Kenaga, Lucius J., 1853-; Long, Eli; Miller, Christian F., 1834-; Reist, Elias; Reist, John, d.1879; Wickens, Lillian Kenaga, 1860-; Zimmerman, John B.; Baer family; Kanagy family; Reist family
- Correspondence, 1851-1908; Series I; 1.5; (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is alphabetically arranged by surname with unidentified letters placed at the end. Separate listings have generally been given for individuals writing two or more letters. Single letters of individuals have been placed in "Letter" general files.
  - "A-B" general, 1866-1904,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baer, Benjamin F., 1877-1907, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
  - Baer, David and Mary E., 1854-67, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baer, Goldie, 1898-1902 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baer, Jasper, 1907 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Baer, Joseph, 1854-1903, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Baer, Levi W., 1862-65 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Barnes, Ed S., 1877, 1886, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Barton, Elizabeth Reist, 1868-98 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Beam, Abner C., 1877 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brown, J. H., 1900-02 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brubaker, Daniel, 1877, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cadwell, Jerome B., 1873 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Casler, Joanna Kenaga, 1874-1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chaffee, Una Kenaga, 1899, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chapton, D., 1872 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cook, Eliza Segar, 1853-55 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cundy, William, 1877-78 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Curtis, Mary, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "D-E" general, 1874, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Enders, Harry H., 1875, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "F" general, 1863-1901 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Fogelsonger, Elias, 1861-71 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fogelsonger, George, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Fogelsonger, Jefferson, 1867, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fogelsonger, John M., 1866-67 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fogelsonger, Nathaniel, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fogelsonger, Sarah Kenaga, 1864-1903 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Foster, C. T., 1884-85 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Frick, Christian S., 1864-90 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Frick, Elma, 1878, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Frick, Fanny H. and Martin, 1897, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Frick, Susan Reist, 1866-1902, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - "G" general, 1859-77 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hicks, W. P., 1903-04 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "K" general, 1860, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Kenaga, Allen Elmer, 1891-1904 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - Kenaga, Daniel Hitt, 1903-04 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Kenaga, Ester, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Kenaga, Fanny Reist, 1857-85, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48-52)
  - Kenaga, Isaac Newton, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Kenaga, Ira Eugene, 1885-1905 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Kenaga, J. B., 1895 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Kenaga, Jacob, 1854-62 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Kenaga, John, 1858-77, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Kenaga, Joseph, 1856-79 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Kenaga, Levi, 1856-89, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59-65)
  - Kenaga, Lucius J., 1876-1907 (Box 2, Folder 66-68)
  - Kenaga, Otto L., 1895-1906 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Kisselbrous, David, 1867-68 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - "L" general, 1863-1900, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Leech, Albert F., 1903-04 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Lockwood, Maria Miller, 1853-97 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Lockwood, Nelson A., 1901, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Lockwood, Susan Kenaga, 1877-1908 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Long, Benjamin A., 1862, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Long, Eli, 1862-1907, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77-78)
  - "M" general, 1859-91 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Miller, Christian F., 1854-1907 (Box 3, Folder 80-86)
  - Miller, William S., 1867-85 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Mothersill, J. W., 1893, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Munger, C. A., 1903 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - "N" general, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Osborn, D. M. & Co., 1881-91 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - "P" general, 1868-92 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Pearce, Eliza G., 1853-54 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Penfoldt, William, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Peters, George, 1884-99, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - The Plymouth Iron Windmill Company, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - "R" general, 1867-83 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Rapp, Charles, 1851, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Reist, Christian, 1851, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Reist, Daniel, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Reist, Ellen, 1886, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Reist, Elias, 1864-98 (Box 3, Folder 102-05)
  - Reist, Jacob, 1871-79 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Reist, John and Anna, 1866-77 (Box 3, Folder 107-09)
  - Reist, Sabina, 1889, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - "S" general, 1888-89, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Salter, M. B., 1871-76 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Segar, Barbara, 1866-84 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Shank, Abraham, 1854-55 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Synder, Jacob W., 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Synder, Lillian L., 1892-1904 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Staley, Henry A., 1862-63 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Stark, Frank, 1898-99 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Steinbaugh, Frank, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Stever, Tobias, 1857-58 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Strohm, Abraham, 1858-59 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Strohm, Jacob H., 1860-78 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - "T" general, 1884, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Vogel, H. F., 1885-86 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - "W" general, 1863-90 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Wickens, Charles L., 1883-1906, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Wickens, Lillian Kenaga, 1882-1901 (Box 4, Folder 126-27)
  - Wiede, Louis, 1872-99 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Witmer, Martin, 1854, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Zimmerman, Fannie A., 1879 Sep 10 (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Zimmerman, John B., 1855-1903 (Box 4, Folder 131-32)
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1867-1902, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 133)
- Other Papers, 1853-1904; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series II, Other Papers, is alphabetically arranged by subject, except for an item level list of letters at the end of the series.
  - Advertisements, 1873-89, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134-35)
  - Insurance
    - Citizens' Mutual Fire Insurance Company, 1901, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Michigan Mutual Tornado, Cyclone and Wind-storm Insurance Company, 1903-04 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - State Insurance Company, 1867 (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1875-1904, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - Pension papers, 1887-1904 (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Photographs, 1864, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - Political literature, 1886, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - Regimental orders, 1864-65 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Subscriptions
    - The Amherst Bee, 1880-1900 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Brother Jonathan, 1853, 1887, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - The Buffalo Courier, 1892, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Street & Smith, 1888, 1897, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - The Sun (New York City), 1872, 1886, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - List of letters, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149-51)